<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The patterne of an inuincible faith A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the first Sunday after Trinity, being the 2d. of Iune. 1616. By VVilliam VVorship, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Worship, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120350</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855549</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The patterne of an inuincible faith A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the first Sunday after Trinity, being the 2d. of Iune. 1616. By VVilliam VVorship, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Worship, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Matthew Law, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Churchyard at the signe of the Fox,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Lower half of title page torn away.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21044:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21044:1"/>
            <p>THE PATTERNE OF AN INVIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIBLE FAITH.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at Paules Croſſe, the firſt Sunday after Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, being the 2<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> of Iune. 1616.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM WORSHIP, Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSALME 17. 6. <hi>I haue called vpon thee: ſurely thou wilt heare me, ô GOD.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21044:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21044:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR <hi>FRANCIS BACON,</hi> KNIGHT, ONE OF HIS MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES MOST HONOVRABLE PRIVIE COVNSELL</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Honourable, there is no child of <hi>GOD,</hi> but either hath, or muſt ſhortly wraſtle with <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi> A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict ſo terrible, that not onely the ſweat will bubble through the brow; but the very bloud will trickle downe within the ribbes.<note place="margin">Iob. 6. 4.</note> Thus <hi>Iob</hi> was a <hi>Butt</hi> for the <hi>Almighty</hi> to ſhoot at: Oh, his ſpirit was drunke vp with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim of his Arrowes.<note place="margin">Pſa. 77 9. 10. 6. 3. 38. 2. 3.</note> How oft was <hi>Dauid</hi> at the brim of deſpaire? what cryings, what roarings were there, before his conſcience could he ſtill'd?<note place="margin">Iſa. 38. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Hezechias</hi> chatters like a <hi>Crane,</hi> or <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>llow,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord brake his bones in peec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> bitterly weepes,<note place="margin">Mat 26 75. Luke 18. 13. Rom 7. 24. 1. Tim. 1. 13.</note> the <hi>Publican</hi> thumpes himselfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Paul</hi> cannot leaue his ſighing, to think of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Perſecution,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> the curſed fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21044:3"/> his former ignorance. For <hi>Preparation</hi> againſt this <hi>Agonie,</hi> I thought it fit to treat of the rare <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Syro-Phoenician,</hi> in that ſolemne and Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Aſſembly, whereunto I was newly cal'd. Whereon while my thoughts were attending, I was ſuddenly caſt vpon my bed of ſickneſſe, and ſo became more diſabled for ſo great a taske, which yet I ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to performe, as the Lord gaue vtterance.</p>
            <p>And being by ſome intreated to divulge it, I vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denied, as conſcious of mine owne wants; when loe, receiuing ſome inckling of your Honours fauour towards me, I aduentured to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate this poore <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> to your name, as deſirous to congratulate with the reſt of the Sonnes of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> this iuſt amplification of your deſerued honour. And ſo the boldneſſe of <hi>Loue,</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> hath ſent out this meane, and ſlender <hi>Tractate,</hi> to one of the moſt <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Iudgments,</hi> and <hi>Heroical Spirits</hi> vnder Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>With my daily prayers for the continuance, and encreaſe of true bleſsings to your <hi>Honour,</hi> I humbly take leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours euer in all duetie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance, WILLIAM WORSHIP.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21044:3"/>
            <head>THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>MATH. 15. 22. &amp;c.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>22 <hi>And behold, a woman of Canaan, came out of the ſame Coaſts, and cryed vnto him, ſaying, Haue mercy on mee, ô Lord thou Sonne of</hi> Dauid, <hi>my daughter is miſerably vexed with a deuill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>23 <hi>But he anſwered her not a word. And his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples came and beſought him, ſaying, ſend her away, for ſhe cryeth after vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>24 <hi>But he anſwered, and ſaid, I am not ſent, but vnto the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>25 <hi>Yet ſhee came and worſhipped him, ſaying, Lord helpe mee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>26 <hi>But hee anſwered and ſaid; It is not meet to take the childrens bread, and to caſt it to Dogges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>27 <hi>And ſhe ſaid, Truth Lord, yet the Dogges eat of the crummes that fall from their maiſters table.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>28 <hi>Then Ieſus anſwered, and ſaid vnto her, O wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man! great is thy</hi> Faith: <hi>bee it vnto thee euen as thou wilt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow was the time that the day began to dawne, when the beames of Chriſts grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to bee ſhed vpon the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> The Scribes and Phariſes (the Diuines of Iury) through <hi>Enuy</hi> and <hi>Maliciouſneſſe,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne not the worth of the Meſſiah. They hold
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21044:4"/> hold him but <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> or elſe but <hi>Chryſtall,</hi> or but white <hi>Saphir</hi> at the beſt; when in truth hee is a <note n="*" place="margin">So <hi>Luther</hi> cals him, in his Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 2 to the <hi>Galatians.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diamond.</hi> For as the <hi>Diamond</hi> is the chiefe of <hi>Gemmes:</hi> ſo <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is the chiefe of <hi>Men.</hi> As the colour of the Diamond is properly of no colour; ſo the comming of Chriſt was without any ſhew. As there is nothing more white then the light of the Diamond, nothing more blacke then his ſhadow; ſo nothing more glorious then Chriſt in his Tranſfiguration, nothing more ſad then Hee in his Paſſion. Yet as a Diamond ſet on blacke tent, or pitch, changeth not his hue, as any other ſtone would doe; ſo Chriſt on the Croſſe, in Death, in the Graue, is ſtill the ſame without variation. And as the Diamond yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to the Hammer, nor to the File, nor to the Fire, nor ſcarſe to Time it ſelfe; ſo Chriſt is inuincible, laſting, Euerlaſting. Then <hi>Cleopatraes</hi> Pearle is worth two hundred and fifty thouſand Crownes, howſoeuer the Hog trample it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot; and Chriſt is here highly prized by an Aliant, although the Iewes make no reckoning of Him.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtorie conſiſts of three parts: a <hi>Protaſis,</hi> an <hi>Epitaſis,</hi> a <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Protaſis,</hi> or Ground worke, is in the 22 verſe, and contain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, <hi>A Note of Attention, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Petitioner, a Deſcription of the Party ſued to, and the Summe of the Supplication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Epitaſis,</hi> or Buſie part, comprehends the diuers <hi>Repulſes,</hi> or <hi>Diſcouragements</hi> of the ſaid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21044:4"/> Suppliant; where are alſo inter-wouen many rare, and incomparable vertues, to the 28 verſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> or Cloſe, containes as well <hi>An high Commendation of the Petitioner,</hi> as <hi>A cheerefull Grant of her Deſire,</hi> in the laſt verſe.</p>
            <p>The Text is long, and full of matter; I will ſtriue to be ſhort, but dare not too curſorie, leſt I huddle vp the meſſage of my Heauenly Maiſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Behold.</hi> This Behold, in this place, giues euery one of vs an hub by the elbow, and cals on vs to attend. How attend?<note place="margin">Iugu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> tels vs; with <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> with <hi>willingneſſe,</hi> with <hi>obedience:</hi> With <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi> that we may come to the kernell of the Word; with <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> for God loues a cheerefull hearer; with <hi>obedience</hi> as the end of both, for without <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> He therefore that hath <hi>eares to heare, let him heare;</hi> and let him heare <hi>Now,</hi> this very Sermon, this preſent Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, leſt the Lord cut him off that he neuer heare Preacher more, or at leaſt take away his hearing, which is worſe then if he loſt his limbes, or his eye-ſight. For wanting them, hee might bee carried to the Church; where, if hee could not get in for the preſſe, yet he might be let downe with cordes (before the Preacher) as was the man that was ſicke of the Palſie,<note place="margin">Marke 2. 4.</note> and ſo receiue comfort. It were but taking of ſoftly the leades, in ſome places the tyles, in ſom (alas) the thatche; but when the ſenſe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21044:5"/> is gone, then farewell the ſound of the word Preached, the moſt delicate, and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Muſick that euer was.</p>
            <p>The Petitioner whom we are to behold, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by her <hi>Sex,</hi> by her <hi>Country,</hi> by her <hi>Faith,</hi> and by her <hi>Zeale.</hi> By her <hi>Sex, Behold a woman:</hi> not for the blaze of beauty, which perhaps ſhee wanted; but for the Commemoration, and Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of her vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 48. 2. 36. 3. 8.</note>The Euangeliſts mention many excellent women: the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> her coſen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> old <hi>Anna, loanna, Suſanna,</hi> others: which ſerues as a choake-peare for thoſe ſcurrill mates, that are euer ſharpening their pens, like quils of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupines</hi> againſt <hi>woman-kind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Math.</hi> 14.</note>Ye wanton <hi>Dames,</hi> that are in your ful-blowne pride, looke vpon <hi>this Woman.</hi> Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaies, that when yee are hoyting, and dancing, <hi>the Deuill dances among you;</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> tels you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Diſcipl. &amp; hab. virg.</hi>
               </note> that this <hi>Pargetting of faces,</hi> is <hi>Opus Diaboli, The worke of the Deuill.</hi> Shortly ſhall you finde, that your outward hue is but momentanie, and when the floure is gone, your ſelues may not abide the ſtalke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 46.</note>If now we aske what <hi>Country woman</hi> this <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner</hi> is, it is anſwered <hi>A Cananite. Can any good thing come out of Nazareth?</hi> out of <hi>Canaan?</hi> Yes, the <hi>beſt Man</hi> that euer was, came out of that; and one of the beſt women that euer was, comes out of this. Loe heere the wonderfull ſecrecie of Gods dealing;<note place="margin">Ierem. 7. 4. 5.</note> when <hi>Iury</hi> failes, <hi>Syrophoenicia</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21044:5"/> 
               <hi>The Temple, the Temple, the Temple,</hi> cry the <hi>Iewes;</hi> as if the <hi>Arke</hi> were not before captiuated; as if the <hi>Temple</hi> were not afterward burnt; as if GOD were tied to <hi>Places,</hi> when the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> proue <hi>Apoſtataes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Catholickes,</hi> (whom we tearme ſo by way of <hi>Charientiſme,</hi> as <hi>Davus</hi> is cal'd a <hi>Good fellow,</hi> in the <hi>Comedie)</hi> are euer vpbraiding vs with an <hi>Innouation</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> when, in trurh, it is nothing but a <hi>Renouation.</hi> O, ſay they, where was your <hi>Church,</hi> I pray you, for certaine hundred yeares together, before <hi>Luther</hi> ſtart vp? As if the <hi>Church</hi> ceaſed to be at all, becauſe ſomtimes it ceaſes to be <hi>Viſible.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Is there no <hi>Moone,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin)</hi> at the <hi>change,</hi> becauſe it is then vndiſcernable?<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 19.</note> Did not GOD reſerue <hi>ſeuen thouſand</hi> to himſelfe, when <hi>Eliah</hi> complain'd he was left alone? Who would haue thought there had been <hi>Chriſtians</hi> among the <hi>Canaanites?</hi> Yet you ſee here is one, and why might there not be more? I will vrge them yet further. Haue we none at this day, of our religion thinke they, in <hi>Italy?</hi> Nay, what if there be ſome of them in <hi>Rome?</hi> What if in the <hi>Popes Palace?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> All the <hi>Saints</hi> ſalute you, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> moſt of all, they that are of <hi>Caeſars</hi> houſhold. If in the Court of <hi>Nero</hi> there be <hi>Saints,</hi> then why not in the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angell?</hi> vnleſſe the <hi>Pope</hi> be more cruell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> then that <hi>Monſter,</hi> as, I proteſt, I thinke he is.</p>
            <p>But we are not ſo hard ſet, but that wee can name <hi>Hundreds</hi> for a need, that held with vs in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21044:6"/> the <hi>darkeſt</hi> times; as <hi>All the Churches of Greece,</hi> who renounced <hi>Rome</hi> for her abhominable <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> in the yeare of our <hi>Lord</hi> 1230. Alſo, the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes,</hi> who were diſperſed ouer all this part of the World. And further, thoſe that followed <hi>Iohn Wickliffe,</hi> whoſe number muſt neds bee great, for that he was ſupported by <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> and diuerſe of the <hi>Nobilitie.</hi> To theſe be added the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who with great vehemencie reſiſted the <hi>Papacie.</hi> This poynt hath beene manfully defended by many of the <hi>Lords Champions,</hi> who haue tempeſted aloft furiouſly with their <hi>Ordnance,</hi> and ſent ſmouldring <hi>Bullets,</hi> to whiſtle the newes of <hi>Death</hi> in the eares of the <hi>Enemie:</hi> for me, it is ſufficient, if with this little <hi>Birding-peece,</hi> charg'd but with a thimble-full of <hi>Shot,</hi> I haue taken an eye, or ſpread a few <hi>Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holes</hi> in his face.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>Faith</hi> of this good <hi>Woman,</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by her comming to <hi>Chriſt. Chriſt</hi> would haue beene hid, ſaith S. <hi>Marke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7. 24.</note> but <hi>He could not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 21.</note> for hee is a <hi>Roſe,</hi> euen the <hi>Roſe</hi> of <hi>Sharon,</hi> and whereſoeuer <hi>He</hi> remaines, <hi>He</hi> caſts abroade a fragrancie that diſcouers <hi>Him.</hi> If the <hi>Iron</hi> once ſtirre, and begin to heaue, you may be ſure the <hi>Load-ſtone</hi> is not far of: ſince this <hi>Woman</hi> hies her ſo to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is not of <hi>Nature,</hi> but of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the cauſe of her approach, is the <hi>Attractiue</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Gods Spirit.</hi> This <hi>Faith</hi> is that, which in all the body of this <hi>Text,</hi> is moſt comfortably dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuf'd, as the <hi>Bloud</hi> in the <hi>Veines,</hi> that I ſhall bee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21044:6"/> ſtill occaſion'd to commend it. And let no man thinke much: for of <hi>Faith</hi> it may be truely ſaid, which the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> writes of <hi>Vniuerſall Iuſtice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ethic.</hi> 5. 1.</note> that it containes <hi>All</hi> vertues in it:</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>Nor is the <hi>Euening,</hi> nor the <hi>Morning ſtarre</hi> ſo admirable as it.</p>
            <p>In the meane time thus much: It is the nature of <hi>Faith</hi> in diſtreſſe to go to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> not with <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam 28. 8. 1. King. 1. 2. Iohn. 6. 68.</note> to the <hi>Witch</hi> of <hi>Endor,</hi> nor with <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> to the God of <hi>Ekron. Maiſter,</hi> to whom ſhall wee goe (ſaith <hi>Peter?) Thou</hi> haſt the words of eternall life. <hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>Eamus poſt Chriſtum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard) quia veritas eſt; per Chriſtum, quia via eſt; ad Chriſtum, quia vita eſt: Let vs go after Chriſt, becauſe He is the Truth; by Chriſt, becauſe He is the Way; to Chriſt, becauſe He is the Life.</hi> What good thing can our ſoules deſire, but is to be found in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> Would wee haue <hi>Saluation?</hi> It's in his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Name.</hi> The <hi>Gifts</hi> of the <hi>Spirit?</hi> They are in his <hi>Vnction. Puritie?</hi> It's in his <hi>Conception. Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence?</hi> It's in his <hi>Natiuitie. Redemption?</hi> It's in his <hi>Paſsion. Abſolution?</hi> It's in his <hi>Condemnation. Freedome</hi> from the <hi>Curſe?</hi> It's in his <hi>Croſſe. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction?</hi> It's in his <hi>Sacrifice. Purgation?</hi> It's in his <hi>Bloud. Mortification?</hi> It's in his <hi>Buriall. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uification?</hi> It's in his <hi>Reſurrection. Heauen?</hi> It's in his <hi>Aſcenſion.</hi> Then harſh bee the voyce that ſoundeth not of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> bitter be the ſweets that reliſh not of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yea diſmall be the day, and deſolate bee the night wherein our hearts are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21044:7"/> eſtranged from CHRIST.</p>
            <p>For this <hi>Womans Zeale,</hi> it is here: <hi>She cried. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudentis eſt clamoribus ſtrepere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr. de O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rat. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi>
                  </note> It's a token of Impudencie, to be clamorous in prayer.</hi> True: but <hi>Neceſsity is the mother of Diſpenſation.</hi> Beſides, <hi>Amor ordinem neſcit, Loue knowes no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom.</hi>
               </note> and, <hi>Exceſsivus amor rationem non penſat,</hi> ſay the <hi>Schoole-men, Exceſsiue Loue regards not the rule of Reaſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 8.</note> The <hi>Prophet Dauid</hi> would ſometimes <hi>roare</hi> in his prayer:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5. 16.</note> and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, that the prayer of a righteous man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth much if it be <hi>Feruent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 30. Pſal. 141. 2.</note> For as <hi>Incenſe</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Fire,</hi> makes no ſmell, and therfore is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſacrificed with fire: ſo <hi>Praier</hi> without <hi>Zeale,</hi> ſends vp no pleaſant ſauour to the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Deſcription of the Partie ſued to,</hi> is in this clauſe,<note place="margin">Math. 20. 30. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O Lord, thou Sonne of Dauid:</hi> which very words are vſed by the two <hi>Blinde</hi> men in the 20 of this Goſpell. This Title <hi>Lord,</hi> is (as <hi>Bernard</hi> cals it) <hi>Nomen Maieſtativum,</hi> a <hi>Name of Maieſty,</hi> and is giuen to the <hi>Sonne</hi> of GOD by an <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> becauſe <hi>He</hi> is our Lord, by the <hi>Right of Inheritance,</hi> by the <hi>Right of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> and by the <hi>Right of Marriage;</hi> and therefore is the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> in regard of <hi>Order,</hi> as being the <hi>Firſt-born</hi> among his <hi>Brethren;</hi> In regard of <hi>Perfection,</hi> both for his <hi>ſublimitie</hi> &amp; <hi>fulnes</hi> of <hi>Grace;</hi> and in regard of <hi>Vertue,</hi> for that a certaine <hi>influence</hi> is deriued from him to all the members of his Church. And <hi>Hee</hi> is called <hi>Lord,</hi> not <hi>Denominatiuely,</hi> but <hi>Eſſentially:</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21044:7"/> the right conceiuing whereof, is required a ſtedfaſt beleefe of his God-head, againſt thoſe execrable Heretickes, <hi>Ebion, Cerinthu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Berillus, Samoſatenus, Marcianus, Photinus, Arius, Seruet, Francis Dauid,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Anti-trinitaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> of this time.</p>
            <p>And here obſerue, how honourably this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thinkes of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Shee cals him Lord, the <hi>Iewes Beelzebub:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10. 25.</note> Yet ſhe was an <hi>Heathea,</hi> they <hi>Circumciſed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 28.</note> Shee an <hi>Out-caſt,</hi> they of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ſhee nuzled vp in groſſe <hi>Idolatry,</hi> they trayned vp in the <hi>Law</hi> from their child-hood; ſhe but of ſmall and ſlender knowledge, they learned men, and ſubtle Diſputers. Good Lord, how ſtrong art thou in weakneſſe, and how thou chooſeſt the things that are not, to bring to paſſe the things that are:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Conſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Etiam ſic Domine, etiam ſic; Euen ſo ô Lord,</hi> becauſe it is thy will; whoſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings are often ſecret, alwaies iuſt.</p>
            <p>Now where ſhee ſalutes <hi>Him,</hi> by the name of the <hi>Sonne of Dauid,</hi> it is euident that ſhee takes him to bee the promiſed <hi>Meſsiah.</hi> For all <hi>Iurie</hi> rang of this,<note place="margin">Iohn 7. 42.</note> that <hi>The Chriſt ſhould come of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of Dauid.</hi> Which ſhee hearing at an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, aſſiſted by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and weighing all circumſtances aright, concludes that <hi>This is He.</hi> Which declares her faith to bee holy and aduiſed, well grounded vpon the promiſes of <hi>God,</hi> and not a fleeting, and vapourous imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This is that which is written in the very beginning of the Goſpell: <hi>The Booke</hi> (that is, the <hi>Catalogue,</hi> or <hi>Regiſter)<note place="margin">Math. 1. 1.</note> of the Generation of</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21044:8"/> IESVS CHRIST <hi>the Sonne of</hi> DAVID: As if Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ſhould point with his finger to the <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> and cry, <hi>Behold, this Man</hi> ſo poore, and ſo contemptible in ſhew, is lineally deſcended from the <hi>Kings of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and is the onely <hi>Redeemer of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A wonderfull Myſterie, that GOD ſhould be manifeſted in the fleſh;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 16.</note> yet is it the ſtaffe and pillar of our comfort. Therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes,<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 3.</note> that <hi>Chriſt was made of the ſeed of Dauid:</hi> Not that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> conceiued Him through the pleaſure of carnall deſire, but through faith, remaining ſtill in her chaſteneſſe and integrity; euen as the <hi>Church</hi> (in a kind of Imitation) brings forth children to GOD, and is yet a Virgin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Auſtin</hi> excellently noteth.</p>
            <p>Then here is a Towell thruſt into the throates of <hi>Valentine, Marcion, Manichaeus, Apollinaris,</hi> and other peſtilent Heretickes, who ſtand vp againſt the truth of <hi>Chriſts Humanity:</hi> And more, there is miniſtred a ſweet <hi>Repoſe</hi> for a troubled conſcience. For what keepes me from diſpaire, when Satan claps hold on mee, with his bloudy ſleeue, and his great Butchers knife a-croſſe his mouth, but this, that my <hi>Sauiour</hi> is the <hi>Sonne of Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 17. Gal. 1. 4.</note> a mercifull, and faithfull <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> who hath <hi>giuen himſelfe for my ſinnes.</hi> Hee hath <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Satan,</hi> vnderſtand'ſt thou that? not <hi>receiued,</hi> not <hi>exacted.</hi> Hee hath giuen <hi>Himſelfe; Himſelfe, Satan,</hi> mark'ſt thou that? not <hi>Siluer,</hi> not <hi>Gold,</hi> not <hi>Paſchall Lambes,</hi> not <hi>Angels.</hi> For my <hi>Sinnes,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21044:8"/> 
               <hi>Satan,</hi> mind'ſt thou that? Not for my <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> not for my <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi> For <hi>My</hi> ſinnes, <hi>Satan,</hi> hear'ſt thou that? as well as for <hi>Paules,</hi> or for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> For though they were a thouſand times more <hi>Sanctified</hi> then I; yet were they neuer a whit more <hi>Iuſtified</hi> then I: And the goodneſſe they had, came not from themſelues, but from GOD, who hath put into my heart a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, not of Heauen onley (for ſo had <hi>Balaam)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23. 10.</note> but of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> which the <hi>Reprobate</hi> cannot haue. Thus if in our <hi>Agonies,</hi> wee ſhall latch the blowes of our ghoſtly Aduerſarie, wee may boldly look for that <hi>Crowne of Righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 8.</note> 
               <hi>which the Lord hath promiſed to thoſe that loue his appearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Summe of her Petition</hi> is ſet downe two waies; <hi>Indefinitely</hi> and <hi>Determinately. Indefinitely</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Haue mercy on me:</hi> Where ſhee ſues in <hi>forma Pauperis,</hi> and pleades for <hi>Mercy,</hi> not <hi>Merit,</hi> though ſhe was one of the godlieſt women in all the world. Yet you know <hi>(Beloued)</hi> who ſtand vpon the <hi>Merit of Condignity,</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (and that from their Councell of <hi>Trent)</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Trid. Sect</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. 1. Cor. 9. 16.</note> that they haue <hi>Faculty</hi> giuen them <hi>perfectly to fulfill the Law.</hi> Nay the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> go further, and will ſtand to it, that they are able to doe more then the <hi>Ten Commandements</hi> require. They talke of <hi>Puritans,</hi> but if theſe be not <hi>pure pute Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophants,</hi> and the white ſonnes of <hi>Novatus,</hi> the <hi>ROMAN Preſbyter,</hi> who are? To whom not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding (to doe them a fauour) wee will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21044:9"/> chaine the <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> after whom ſhall come the <hi>Browniſt</hi> in a ſtring, who is halfe an <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> as the <hi>Tadpole</hi> is halfe a <hi>Frogge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, for vs poore <hi>Publicanes,</hi> wee will not truſt to our deſerts (which will ſhelter vs no more then an Arbour in Winter) but to GODS <hi>tender compaſsion.</hi> What though my ſinnes bee as red as bloud, as blacke as Haire-cloth, as Pitch, as Hell; Yet are they not <hi>Infinit,</hi> as is GODS <hi>Mercie.</hi> Onely I muſt <hi>Repent,</hi> that is, confeſſe, and forſake my ſinnes, and turne with my whole heart, not faynedly, to the Lord. For our <hi>Sauiour</hi> chargeth his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> to Preach <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Remiſsion of ſinnes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 24. 47.</note> So that no <hi>Repentance,</hi> no <hi>Forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> I know the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is a <hi>Booke of Mercie:</hi> I know that in the <hi>Prophets</hi> there are many aſperſions of <hi>Mercy:</hi> I know that <hi>Out of the Eater comes Meat, and out of the Strong comes Sweetneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 14. 14.</note> and that in the <hi>Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (which bee the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> of <hi>Death)</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 7.</note> there is made expreſſe mention of Mercy, <hi>I will haue mercy vpon Thouſands;</hi> Yea, the very firſt words of them are the <hi>Couenant</hi> of <hi>Grace, I am the Lord THY God:</hi> Yet if euery Leafe, and euery Line, and euery Word in the <hi>Bible,</hi> were nothing but <hi>Mercy, Mercy,</hi> it nothing auailes the <hi>Preſumptuous ſinner,</hi> that lies rotting in his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. Our GOD is not an impotent GOD, with one Arme, but as <hi>Hee is ſlow to anger,</hi> ſo is <hi>Hee great in Powre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nahum 1. 3.</note> and will not ſurely cleere the wicked. O but he is <hi>Mercifull, Gracious, ſlow to</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21044:9"/> 
               <hi>anger, aboundant in goodneſſe, and truth, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mercy for thouſands, forgiuing iniquity, and tranſgreſsion, and ſinne:</hi> Is not here <hi>Mercy</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nine, or ten times together? It is: But reade on to the very next words; <hi>And not making the wicked innocent, viſiting the iniquity of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vpon the children, and vpon childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnto the third and fourth generation.</hi> Is not this the terrible voyce of <hi>Iuſtice?</hi> But ſtay: in the hundred thirty and ſix <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 136.</note> there is nothing but, <hi>His mercy endureth for euer, His mercy endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euer: His mercy endureth for euer,</hi> is the foote of the <hi>Song,</hi> and is found ſix and twenty times, in ſix and twenty verſes. It is: Yet harko what a ratling thunder-clap is heere.<note place="margin">15. 17. 18. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>And ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw</hi> Pharoah, <hi>and his Hoſt in the Red Sea; and ſmete great Kings, and ſlew mighty Kings,</hi> Sihon <hi>King of the Amorites, and</hi> Og, <hi>the King of Baſhan.</hi> Therefore <hi>(Beloued)</hi> if wee will haue mercy at the <hi>Tribunall Seate</hi> of GOD, let vs humble our ſelues for our <hi>manifold</hi> and <hi>bloudie</hi> ſinnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nec quiſquam peccatis retardetur, aut annis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian: And let no man hold off,</hi> for that his offences are heynous, and that hee is old, and moſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne in them: onely let him beware of <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,</hi> and <hi>Delay,</hi> which will cheat the ſoule, and bring it to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Part</hi> of the <hi>Petition</hi> which is put downe <hi>Determinatly,</hi> is in theſe words, <hi>My Daughter is miſerably vexed with a Deuill.</hi> Where ſhee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly beſeeches <hi>Chriſt,</hi> euen in the bowels of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21044:10"/> 
               <hi>compaſsion</hi> to behold her <hi>Child,</hi> her <hi>little Child,</hi> as Saint <hi>Marke</hi> hath it,<note place="margin">Marke. 7. 23.</note> and to diſlodge an vncleane, and raging <hi>Spirit,</hi> who had taken vp her body as a <hi>Cabin</hi> to reſt in. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Where firſt obſerue, that ſhe makes her <hi>Daughters</hi> miſery her owne, <hi>Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on ME, my Daughter.</hi> Acknowledging with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that GOD in chaſtening the fruit of her wombe, had laid his ſcourge vpon her alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe take notice, how it is the nature of loue to <hi>Deſcend,</hi> and how the affection of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> to their <hi>Children,</hi> is farre more deere then that of <hi>Children</hi> to their <hi>Parents.</hi> We reade heere in this, and in ſundry other places of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> how carefully <hi>Parents</hi> made meanes to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for the chaſing away of <hi>Deuils,</hi> and <hi>diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> from their <hi>Children;</hi> but where reade yee that the <hi>Children</hi> did the like for their <hi>Parents?</hi> In the eighth of this <hi>Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 21.</note> there's a <hi>ſonne</hi> intreates our <hi>Sauiour</hi> that hee may <hi>go bury his Father,</hi> that he may throw Moulds on him, and make him ſure: but he neuer once prayed him to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le him when hee was ſick, or raiſe him when he was dead.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Marke further, how ſore, and ſtrange af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions befall ſometimes GODS deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Woe, and alas, here's a furious Deuill, that poſſeſſeth the body of this womans <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> If he had onely haunted the houſe, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly wrought vpon her child, the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had beene grieuous, but to enter into her with his very ſubſtance, is moſt lamentable to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21044:10"/> thinke on. And yet the <hi>Lord</hi> thus correcteth her in <hi>Loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 6.</note> in <hi>Loue</hi> (I ſay) howſoeuer it ſeeme a <hi>Paradox</hi> to <hi>Reaſon.</hi> O, it's an heauy iudgement of GOD, when a man thriues in ſinne, and when in the midſt of his rebellions, hee ſpreads him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt the <hi>Sunne,</hi> like an <hi>Apricock.</hi> When the anger of GOD waxed hot againſt the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> hee threatens that hee will plague them: How plague them? in not plaguing them:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>I will NOT viſite your Daughters when they are Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, nor your Spouſes when they are Whores. Certè tunc magis iraſcitur Deus, cum non iraſcitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Certainely,</hi> GOD <hi>is then moſt angry, when hee ſeemes not angry at all. Miſericordiam hanc nolo; For mine owne part</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I would none of this mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Moreouer note, how <hi>all things worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the beſt to them that loue</hi> GOD.<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28.</note> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Earth, Fire, Water, good Men, bad Men, wilde Beaſts, tame Beaſts, Calmneſſe, Tempeſts, Peace, Warre, Freedome, Thraldome, Wealth, Want, Healthfulneſſe, Crazineſſe, Life, Death, Angels, Deuils.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de Ciu. Dei, lib.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Etiam peccata Domine: Euen our ſins alſo, ô Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſten. Audeo dicere</hi> (ſaith the ſame Father) <hi>ſuperbis eſſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ile, cadere in aliquod apertum, manifeſtum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> peccatum. I dare bee bold to ſpeake it, that it is good that proud men do fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome groſſe and open ſinne, that ſo Shame may driue them to remorſe.</hi> This Doctrine is true; But let no <hi>Spider</hi> ſuck poyſon thence. One wold haue thought that this woman, who was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21044:11"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> wold haue laid the blame on her <hi>Religion,</hi> and thought hardly of GOD, thus to ſingle her out for a ſpectacle of miſery, and ſcarſe to ſhake his rod at her fellow <hi>Gentiles;</hi> but ſee how this correction brings her neerer to GOD, and how the <hi>Deuill</hi> himſelfe, is a meanes to further her ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, it is obſerueable, that <hi>Sinne</hi> is the moſt fearefull thing in the world. The body of <hi>Man</hi> was made to be the <hi>Temple of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> but <hi>ſinne</hi> makes it a <hi>Stie,</hi> and <hi>Plauncher</hi> for <hi>Satan,</hi> who teares it, wallowes it, and torments it pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, as here,<note place="margin">Verſe. 20</note> and in the ninth of Saint <hi>Marke.</hi> Shall I in one word ſet out the vileneſſe of it? It is a <hi>Deuill.</hi> And why not worſe? For what makes the <hi>Deuill</hi> a <hi>Deuill,</hi> but <hi>Sinne?</hi> Take that away, and hee's a good creature. Beſides, here's a ſingle Deuill in this Childe, without a partner: but ſinne is ſo congregable, that it is impatient of ſolitude.</p>
            <p>Our Father <hi>Adam</hi> eates the forbidden fruit; we would thinke it but one ſinne; but what ſayes <hi>Auſtine?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Enchir.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Superbia eſt illic, &amp; Sacrilegiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Homici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Fornicatio Spiritualis, &amp; Furtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Auaritia: Pride was at the fact, &amp; Sacriledge, &amp; Murder, and Spirituall Fornication, and Theft, and Couetouſnes.</hi> This is the <hi>Diuell</hi> that reignes at this day, in the <hi>Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Diſobedience;</hi> with which yet they play, as with a feather, and take pleaſure in <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> O <hi>Sinne;</hi> thou art delightfull at the firſt, but at laſt thou ſtingeſt, like a <hi>Bee,</hi> like a <hi>Waſpe,</hi> like an <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21044:11"/> like a <hi>Scorpion.</hi> O <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> thou haſt a <hi>Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckle</hi> in thy mouth, but a bitter branch ſticking at thy heart; I would name <hi>Rue,</hi> but that thou haſt nothing to doe with <hi>Hearbe of Grace.</hi> And this of the PROTASIS.</p>
            <p>The EPITASIS followes, wherein we are to weigh the ſundry <hi>Repulſes,</hi> and <hi>Diſcouragements</hi> to weigh the ſundry <hi>Repulſes,</hi> and <hi>Diſcouragements</hi> of this good Woman, together with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant proſecution of her cauſe, as they lye in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>For the firſt <hi>Repulſe,</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> ſayes, that <hi>He</hi> anſwered <hi>Her</hi> not a word. What? not vnfold his lips, to giue one word? O wonderfull tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! For what might ſhee thinke? Is this <hi>Hee</hi> in whom all the Nations of the earth ſhould bee bleſſed?<note place="margin">Gen. 12. 3. Iſaiah 55. 1. 65. 24.</note> Is this <hi>He,</hi> of whom <hi>Proclamation</hi> was made; <hi>Ho, Euery</hi> one that thirſteth, come yee to the <hi>Waters?</hi> Is this <hi>He,</hi> that will heare his ſeruants while they ſpeake, and anſwere before they call? No, no; I ſee my labour is loſt, my hopes degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and my thoughts fruſtrate. I haue look't vp to the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and can ſee no light: I haue hied me to the <hi>Fountaine,</hi> and can finde no water: I haue runne, and cried after the GOD of <hi>All com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> diſdaines to ſpeake the leaſt word to me. Ah, my deere Childe, my heart melts like Wax in the midſt of my bowels, to thinke of thee. Thou art (alas what ſay I? where am I?) thou art (poore wretch) poſſeſſed of a Dieull, and there was hope; but now what ſhall I doe, when the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> ſhuts his eare to my complaint, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21044:12"/> roundly anſweres me in not anſwering me.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhe might haue debated the caſe, but ſhe did not. For though <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſilent; yet in truth, <hi>He</hi> gaue her a double anſwere: the one by the generall promiſes of his word; the other, by the ſecret whiſperings of his <hi>Spirit. Hee</hi> mindes her well enough, but <hi>Hee</hi> makes as though <hi>Hee</hi> heard not, that the precious graces lock't vp in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of her heart, might bee brought forth to light. Beſides, her cries were <hi>Muſicall;</hi> ſo hee is loth to haue them broke off. And more: this <hi>Delay</hi> bred no danger, but wher on her affection, and made the gift more welcome at the receipt; for (vſually) what is hardly got, is greatly ſet by.</p>
            <p>It is euen ſo: the childe of GOD prayes ſometimes on his <hi>Knees,</hi> ſometimes on his <hi>Face,</hi> and that <hi>with ſighes that cannot be expreſſed;</hi> and yet GOD ſeemes not to regard, but rather to be angry at his prayer.<note place="margin">Pſalme 80. 4.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſaith the Church in her affliction) <hi>how long wilt thou bee angry againſt the prayer of thy people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 22. 2.</note> 
               <hi>O my God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) I cry in the day time and thou heareſt not, and in the night ſeaſon I take no reſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered thy ſelfe with a cloud,</hi> ſaith the deſolate <hi>Ieruſalem, that our prayer ſhould not paſſe through.</hi> What then?<note place="margin">Eſay 59. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Is the Lords hand ſhortned that it cannot ſaue? Or his eare heauy, that it cannot heare?</hi> No, <hi>But our Iniquities do ſeparate betweene vs and our GOD, and our ſinnes hide his face from vs, that hee will not heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21044:12"/>
            <p>Sometimes we aske we know not what, with the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10. 22.</note> Sometimes we aske with <hi>doubting, and wauering.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 1. 6.</note> Sometimes wee aske <hi>amiſſe, that wee might conſume it on our luſts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 4. 5.</note> Sometimes we offer a <hi>Dogges-necke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 66. 3.</note> our ſoules delighting in our abhominations. Sometimes (nay almoſt alwaies) wee haue <hi>rouing, and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thoughts,</hi> and ſo no maruell if wee receiue not. <hi>Quomodo te audiri à Deo poſtulas, cûm te ipſe non audias,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. de Orat. Dom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>How dar'ſt thou deſire that GOD ſhould heare thee, when thou heareſt not thy ſelfe? Thou wakeſt</hi> with thine <hi>eyes,</hi> and <hi>ſleepeſt</hi> with thine <hi>Heart:</hi> where a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould wake with his <hi>Heart,</hi> when he ſleepeth with his <hi>Eyes.</hi> But let vs ſtep on to the ſecond <hi>Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then came to Him his Diſciples, and beſought him ſaying, ſend her away, for ſhee cryeth after vs.</hi> Where the <hi>Diſciples</hi> do not entreate <hi>Him</hi> to pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie her, but onely to diſpatch her, one way or other, becauſe ſhe kept ſuch a bawling. Which dealing of theirs, diſcouers their <hi>Curioſity:</hi> for they will needes (for ſooth) teach their <hi>Maiſter</hi> what to do; as though <hi>Hee</hi> leard not as well as they, and would not haue diſmiſt her, had hee thought it conuenient. Thus tampers <hi>Peter,</hi> in a matter of Life and Death (and that Eternall and Vniuerſall)<note place="margin">Math. 16. 22.</note> till our <hi>Sauiour</hi> cals him <hi>Satan</hi> for his paines. But that which I chiefly faſten vpon, from the <hi>Diſciples</hi> indifferency, is the boundleſſe, and bottomeleſſe mercy of GOD,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21044:13"/> which compared with <hi>Mans,</hi> is as the <hi>Ocean</hi> to a <hi>Drop.</hi> Which made <hi>Dauid</hi> in the wonderfull ſtrait of <hi>Three</hi> plagues propounded, to chooſe to fall into the hand of the <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp; not into the hand of <hi>Man.</hi> Theſe <hi>Diſciples</hi> were the friends, and followers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> of the world, the <hi>Patriarkes</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> aſſigned to high, and heauenly <hi>Functions: Mathew</hi> to bee an <hi>Euangeliſt, Peter</hi> an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> an <hi>Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, an Apoſtle,</hi> and a <hi>Prophet:</hi> an <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> in his <hi>Goſpell,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in his <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> a <hi>Prophet</hi> in his <hi>Reuelation.</hi> Then who ſhould be good, if they were euill? who tender-hearted, if they were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull? Yet ſuch ſmall compaſſion harbour'd they in their boſomes, that (ſo ſhe would leaue her clamouring) whether ſhee ſped or no, they car'd not greatly.</p>
            <p>Which makes me wonder, that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſhould bee ſo chub-headed, as to proue from hence the <hi>Invocation</hi> of dead <hi>Saints.</hi> For <hi>firſt,</hi> this <hi>Woman</hi> deſires none of them to ſpeake for her. Secondly, they complaine, they make not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. Thirdly, ſhe is neuer the neerer for their requeſt. Fourthly, ſuppoſe ſhe had far'd the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet I hope there is great difference, between praying to the liuing, and to the dead. Me thinks they ſhould be aſhamed, thus foully to wreſt this <hi>Example;</hi> but who would looke for water from a <hi>Pumice-ſtone,</hi> or vertues bluſh in an <hi>Italianated</hi> cheeke?</p>
            <p>Are theſe the men ſo renowned for <hi>Artes,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21044:13"/> 
               <hi>Tongues, Reading?</hi> Are theſe the <hi>Kil-Cowes</hi> of the world, for learning? Are theſe the beſt <hi>Schollers</hi> of their <hi>Seuen-headed Parnaſſus?</hi> Come, come, the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> (the <hi>Popes Roaring Boyes)</hi> know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough we haue got the ſtart of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they make now no <hi>Syllogiſmes,</hi> but in FE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIO. Yet ſome of our <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that haue made a ſteppe beyond the <hi>Alpes,</hi> looke as bigge as <hi>Bull-beefe,</hi> if we offer to compare with them: and tell vs with a ſhrugge, that <hi>They</hi> haue <hi>Scripture, Councels,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers</hi> on their ſide. But when wee come to the battell, they tell vs from Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that <hi>Scripture</hi> is not a <hi>Rule,</hi> but a <hi>Commonitorie: That it is not ſufficient; That it is not neceſſarie.</hi> Come to <hi>Councels,</hi> we are willing to be iudg'd by the moſt ſacred Councell of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and (in all poynts of Faith) by the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Generall Councels</hi> of <hi>Nice, Conſtantinople, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, Chalcedonia.</hi> They make ſhew of no great diſlike, but at laſt they bring vs to the <hi>Councell</hi> held at <hi>Rome,</hi> vnder <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Three and twentith,</hi> where the <hi>Owle</hi> ſate <hi>Preſident</hi> on the <hi>Beame:</hi> or to the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> where they burnt the <hi>Diuell</hi> in <hi>Iohn Huſſes Mitre:</hi> or to their deare deare <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Trent;</hi> where the <hi>Pope</hi> (againſt all conſcience) was both <hi>Partie,</hi> and <hi>Iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deſcend we to the <hi>Fathers,</hi> they bring forth marching in ſingle file, <hi>Origen, Cyprian, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, Ambroſe, Auſten, Ierome, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and the reſt: and would make vs beleeue they came <hi>Voluntaries,</hi> when in truth they preſt them into
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21044:14"/> the field. Where, when they bid, CHARGE; they giue them two blowes for our one; and S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> (that carries the garland from them all) ioynes cheerefully with vs, and (with ſpeare in wreſt) makes lanes amongſt them. Which they perceiuing, determine the next time to be euen with vs, and to bring forth old Doctors indeed, that will ſtand to them backe, and edge; namely, my Neam <hi>Clement,</hi> and my Neam <hi>Abdy,</hi> and my Neam <hi>Martiall,</hi> and my Neam <hi>Hyppolite,</hi> and my Neam <hi>Amphiloch,</hi> and other ſuch Button<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap't Fathers, as were neuer yet, in <hi>Rerum Natura.</hi> Thus haue I <hi>(Beloued)</hi> vpon occaſion of this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple proofe, (like to which for all the world, bee the reſt of their Arguments) giuen you a ſight of the flouriſhes of the <hi>Catholickes,</hi> (or rather <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licons)</hi> which if it haue beene a <hi>Digreſsion,</hi> I hope it hath beene no <hi>Tranſgreſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now to the <hi>Third Repulſe,</hi> expreſſed in this <hi>Anſwere</hi> of our <hi>Sauiour: I am not ſent but to the loſt Sheepe of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Where <hi>He</hi> renders a reaſon to his <hi>Diſciples</hi> (within the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> hearing) why <hi>Hee</hi> cannot condiſcend to her importunate requeſt, to wit, becauſe it came not within the compaſſe of his <hi>Commiſsion.</hi> For his Father had ſent him, though not onely, yet chiefly to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> of which number ſhe was none (but a <hi>Gentile)</hi> and the <hi>Partition-wall</hi> was not yet broken downe; ſo hee would haue her ſet her heart at reſt, and trouble him no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſince her ſuite was vnreaſonable, if not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21044:14"/> vnreaſonable.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Lord;</hi> this was enough to haue ſplit her heart in peeces. What? <hi>Hee</hi> in whom all health was promiſed, who offred himſelfe to all others, healing all diſeaſes,<note place="margin">Math. 4. 24. 11. 28.</note> and calling all that were weary to <hi>Him,</hi> to take exception againſt her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and to giue ſuch a ſmart, and diſcourteous anſwer, as might put her beſide all hope of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? But this was done, that GODS glory might bee more illuſtrated, and the triall of her faith, (being much more pretious then gold)<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> might be found vnto her praiſe, as the euent teſtified.</p>
            <p>Now where <hi>Chriſt</hi> affirmes, that <hi>He</hi> is ſent to the <hi>loſt Sheepe,</hi> it is manifeſt that he is a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> and that <hi>Shepheard</hi> too, of whom the <hi>Lord</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 23.</note> That <hi>He</hi> will ſet vp a <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard</hi> ouer his <hi>People,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> ſhall <hi>feed</hi> them, euen his ſeruant <hi>Dauid,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 4. Heb. 13. 20.</note> Hee</hi> ſhall <hi>feed</hi> them, and <hi>He</hi> ſhall be their <hi>Shephard.</hi> The ſame is he that is called <hi>The chiefe Shepheard,</hi> and the <hi>Great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of the ſheepe,</hi> to whom all other are but <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſhepheards,</hi> ſubiect to his power, and ſet ouer their charges by his ſpeciall appoyntment. And as <hi>He</hi> is the <hi>Great,</hi> ſo is <hi>He</hi> the <hi>Good Shepheard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10 1. 10 14.</note> for <hi>He</hi> giues his <hi>Life</hi> for his ſheepe. His life? that's much, it is; yet <hi>He</hi> gaue it. Alſo he <hi>knowes</hi> his ſheepe; and that with a double knowledge, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue,</hi> and <hi>Operatiue.<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 13.</note> Contemplatiue;</hi> for all things are naked, and open vnto his eyes: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as naked &amp; as open as the ſheep that hangs vpon the Cambrel, with the skin off, &amp; the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21044:15"/> 
               <hi>Inwards</hi> our, that you may looke on both ſides at your pleaſure; for ſo much the word imports.<note place="margin">Ezek. 34 16.</note> His knowledge is <hi>Operatiue;</hi> for <hi>Hee</hi> prouides good paſture for his ſheep, layes them in a good ſold, ſeekes that which was loſt, brings againe that which was driuen away, bindes vp the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſtrengthens the weake.</p>
            <p>Ye <hi>Shepheards</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> learne of this <hi>Great Good Shepheard;</hi> to tend and tender your flocke.<note place="margin">Prou. 27. 23.</note> Be diligent to know the ſtate of them, as <hi>Salomon</hi> counſels, and feed them with knowledge, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.<note place="margin">Ier. 3. 15.</note> Then goe before them, by example of good life, according to that of <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi> Si mundum praedic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s contemnendum, contemne tu pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs; If thou beat vpon the contempt of the world to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſee firſt that thou contemne it thy ſelfe.</hi> And pray for grace, that you may venter limme, and life for your flockes. <hi>Niſi Chriſtum valde ames</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> (ſaith <hi>Bernard) hoc eſt pluſquam tua, pluſquam tuos, pluſquam Te, nequaquam ſuſcipias curam animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; vnleſſe thou loue Chriſt exceeding deerly, euen better then thy Goods, then thy Kinsfolkes, then thy ſelfe, I would neuer wiſh thee to take vpon thee the Cure of Soules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here giue mee leaue to complaine a little. There are ſome that are yong, and cannot yet preach: others are old, and muſt reſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: others are timorous, and greatly like not ſtanding out for their ſheepe. Are you yong and cannot preach? Nay therefore you ſhould preach; for your bodie is ſtrong, your ſpirits
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21044:15"/> quicke, your VVit freſh, your Memory ſtedfaſt, your Nature bold, and your Voyce tuneable. Are you old, &amp; wold you take leaue of the <hi>Pulpit?</hi> O what pitie were it, that thoſe graue <hi>Fathers,</hi> whoſe Piety, Learning, Sanctimony, Age, hath wonn them ſo great authority, ſhould exhort the <hi>People no more.</hi> For as <hi>Grapes</hi> are not ripe in the <hi>Spring,</hi> nor in <hi>Summer,</hi> but in <hi>Autumne,</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before <hi>Winter:</hi> So the fruits of <hi>Learning</hi> come not to perfection, till old <hi>Age</hi> (the <hi>Virger</hi> of <hi>Death)</hi> ſtep in. And for thoſe that are affraid to hazard themſelues in defence of their Flocke,<note place="margin">Iohn 10. 13.</note> let them remember that hee is an <hi>Hireling,</hi> that ſeeth the <hi>Woolfe</hi> comming, and fleeth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Wolues</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> (ſent out from their <hi>Lycaon)</hi> come leering ouer into the Land, to leap at the throat of that <hi>Princely Sheep,</hi> who is worth <hi>Ten thouſand</hi> of vs;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iliad. a &amp; alibi.</hi>
               </note> who is alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our <hi>Shepheard:</hi> and ſhall wee bee ſuch crauens, and ſo white about the gyls, as not to reſiſt them? O how true is it of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> which <hi>Pius Secundus</hi> (ſometime <hi>Aeneas Syluius)</hi> ſpake of the <hi>Monkes</hi> of his time:
<q>
                  <l>Non audet Stigius Pluto tentare, quod audet Effraenis Monachus:</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The De'ele of Hell dare not attempt the Ill,</l>
                     <l>That an vnbrideled Cloyſter-creeper will.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which makes me not endure thoſe <hi>Newtrals,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21044:16"/> who giue out, that <hi>Wee,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> may be eaſily reconciled: For the truth is, there is ſuch an <hi>Antipathie</hi> betweene a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as there is betweene the two Bird<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch. Mor.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Siſkin,</hi> and the <hi>Muſkin,</hi> which will fight earneſtly aliue, and being dead, if you mix their bloud, it will runne apart, and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Shepheard</hi> is ſent to none but <hi>Sheep,</hi> nay to none but <hi>Loſt Sheep.</hi> The <hi>Sheep</hi> is an innocent, and harmeleſſe creature, the ſame among Beaſts, that the <hi>Doue</hi> is among Birds: So the Childe of GOD muſt bee Meeke, and Gentle, putting away all Bitterneſſe, and Anger, and Wrath, and Crying.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. 31.</note> The <hi>Sheep</hi> is a profitable creature, and euery part of it is good for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: The Wooll for Rayment, the Skin for Parchment, the Fleſh for Meat, the Guts for Muſicke, the Bones for Haftes, and the Hornes to blow downe the walles of <hi>Iericho:</hi> So <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> muſt bee vſefull to the places where they liue, and profitable to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Loſt Sheep</hi> is got into a <hi>maze</hi> of <hi>Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. 16.</note> which GOD ſignifies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when hee compares her to a <hi>Lamb</hi> in a large place. It's in perill of the Woolfe, in perill of the Lyon, in perill of the Thiefe, in perill of the Bryer, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of the Heate, in perill of the Storme, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of the Graſſe, and Water it liues by. So that the ſafety of the poore <hi>Sheep,</hi> conſiſteth onely
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21044:16"/> in the vigilancie of the <hi>Shepheard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Land of ours (through the goodneſſe of GOD) is talkt of farre, and neere for the <hi>Golden Fleece;</hi> for the Marchant knowes, it is a <hi>Colchis.</hi> But that which makes it thrice more famous, is the goodly <hi>Flocke</hi> of <hi>Sheep,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath in it: the fayreſt (I perſwade mee) vnder heauen; Howſoeuer the fowle-mouth'd <hi>Separatiſts</hi> cals vs <hi>Goats,</hi> and <hi>Swine,</hi> and denie vs to bee <hi>Sheep.</hi> What though all of vs carry not a fine Staple on our backes, that will open and ſhut like a pare of Bellowes, are we not therefore <hi>Sheep?</hi> What though ſome of vs bee Rough-coated, ſome Water-wool'd, ſome Totterd, ſome Tackt, ſome Lame, ſome Flye-gal'd, ſome Clouted, ſome Swine-chapt, are we not therefore <hi>Sheep?</hi> VVhat if we be ſtray'd away, and loſt, are we not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Sheep?</hi> Yes we are <hi>Sheep,</hi> though loſt; and it is well that we are <hi>Loſt, for the Son of Man came to ſaue that which was Loſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 18. 11.</note> Then let euery one of vs pray with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, I am gone aſtray, like a ſheepe that is loſt:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 176.</note> Oh ſeek thy ſeruant, for I do not forget thy commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVe are now to ſee how the <hi>Syrophoenician</hi> brookes this harſh anſwere; <hi>Yet ſhe came and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped Him, ſaying, Lord helpe me:</hi> VVhere againe appeares her <hi>Faith</hi> (that eminent vertue) accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with feruent <hi>Prayer,</hi> and with a creeping <hi>Humility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her <hi>Faith</hi> is diſcouered, in that ſhe continues inuoking the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and will not out,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21044:17"/> though <hi>Hee</hi> had declared new before, that <hi>Hee</hi> could not with warrant from his Calling, helpe her; for that GODS <hi>Mercy,</hi> was (for a ſeaſon) confined to the <hi>Iewes.</hi> Her ſpeech is this in effect; O Lord, thou haſt teſtified, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer put their truſt in Thee, ſhall not bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and that whoſoeuer calleth vpon thy Name, ſhall be ſaued: Since I then (miſerable wretch) embrace theſe promiſes of thine by Faith, it is impoſſible that thou ſhouldſt deny me. For though the <hi>Heauen</hi> ſhould wheele out of his place, and the <hi>Earth</hi> ſlip off from her foundation, yet <hi>Thy Word cannot faile.</hi> Then <hi>Lord,</hi> remember me, and all my trouble; pitie the caſe of a poore diſtreſſed woman, and let her teares worke thee to ſome compaſſion: I am reſolu'd; I will take no nay; I am thy <hi>Beggar,</hi> and will haue my <hi>Dole</hi> e're I goe: then thruſt mee not backe, ô bid mee not farewell, for <hi>as the Lord liueth, and as thy ſoule liueth, I will not leaue thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſtrong, and inexpugnable <hi>Faith,</hi> ſends <hi>Prayer</hi> to put the hand in the treaſure of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. O <hi>Prayer</hi> (the moſt excellent fruit of <hi>Faith)</hi> how powerfull art thou with GOD? At <hi>Fiue</hi> ſundry <hi>Petitions,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> Abraham</hi> brought the <hi>Lord</hi> from <hi>Fiftie</hi> to <hi>Ten;</hi> as long as hee prayed, hee was anſwered: And moſt comfortable it is to conſider, that the Lord ceaſed not from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, till <hi>Abraham</hi> ceaſed from asking. Againe, and againe, ſhe cals on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in whom onely
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21044:17"/> ſhe beleeues, and on whom onely ſhee depends for ſuccour. Thus <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſweetly;<note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Lord whom haue I in Heauen but thee; and there is none in earth, that I deſire beſide thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the <hi>Catholickes</hi> at <hi>Loretto,</hi> are alwaies crouching to the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> But what ſayes <hi>Bernard?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Libenter certè glorioſa Virgo tali honore carebit; The glorious Virgin is willingly content to want ſuch honour.</hi> But what talke I of <hi>Loretto?</hi> I would our Ladies (ſome of them) heere at home, were not ſo cunning in their <hi>Ladies Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>O Lady rebuke mee not in thine anger, neither chaſten me in thy diſpleaſure; haue mercy vpon mee, ô Lady, for I am weake, ô Lady help me, for my bones are vexed.</hi> VVhoſe heart doth not quake, whoſe haire doth not ſtand vpright, to thinke that the glorious and fearefull Name of <hi>IEHOVAH,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 58. Deut. 4. 2. 12. 32. Reu. 22. 18.</note> ſhould bee ſpunged out of the <hi>Booke of Pſalmes,</hi> and the title of <hi>Lady</hi> put in, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe charge of GOD, and that vnder the paine of moſt heauy curſes?</p>
            <p>I haue often wondred (and that with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) that the <hi>Popes Creatures</hi> ſhould be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated, as to leaue CHRIST IESVS,<note place="margin">Ier. 2. 13. 27.</note> 
               <hi>the Fountaine of liuing Waters, and to digge them Pits, euen broken Pits, that can hold no water: Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Tree thou art my Father, and to a Stone thou haſt begotten me:</hi> the Scripture euery where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning it, as cleerely, as if it were written with the brighteſt Sunne-beame on a wall of Glaſſe, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaketh. And I could neuer bee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21044:18"/> quieted in my mind, when I ſaw them thus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, till GODS <hi>Prouidence</hi> directed mee to the hundred and fifteene <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the eight verſe,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 115.</note> where I found it thus written: <hi>They that make them, are like vnto them, and ſo are all they that put their truſt in them:</hi> For euer ſince, I thus reaſon with my ſelfe. If I ſhall come to an image of VVood, or Stone, or Mettall, and ſhall call, and ſhout, <hi>Ho, Image! are you aſleepe? What Image, Image! canſt thou not heare? Art thou deafe?</hi> The Image is neuer a whit the wiſer, though I ſhould burſt my lunges with crying, becauſe though it looke like a Man, and haue Eares, yet they are but Eares by <hi>Equivocation.</hi> And euen ſo, if I ſhall ſtriue to conuince a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> with neuer ſuch fulneſſe of Voyce, and forcibleneſſe of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is to no more purpoſe, then the blowing of a Trumpet in the eares of <hi>Baal,</hi> or making a ſet ſpeech to a <hi>Painted Poſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next companion of her <hi>Faith,</hi> is <hi>Humilty:</hi> for ſhe bowes downe her body, and fals at his feet, as if by her geſture ſhe confeſt her ſelfe to be a miſerable ſinner, and had no refuge but in <hi>Humility.</hi> A vertue, that like the <hi>Violet,</hi> is poore in ſhew, growes low by the ground, and hangs the head, as willing to liue vnſeene: Yet is it euer in the way of preferment, as we finde in <hi>Ioſeph, Moſes, Mordecai.</hi> An embleme whereof we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but remember; For wee ſee that the little <hi>Graſſe-hopper</hi> (the ſillieſt of creatures) is yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced in the principall Citie, and in a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21044:18"/> Street of that Citie, and in a principall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that Street, and in a principall place of that Building, as a golden obiect of <hi>Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> to be gazed on.</p>
            <p>But at no time is <hi>Humility</hi> more requiſite, then in Prayer;<note place="margin">1. King 8. 54.</note> therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> a King, prayes vpon his knees (for theſe high <hi>Humilities</hi> are very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to GOD.) <hi>Beloued;</hi> let vs deteſt <hi>Pride,</hi> as a moſt pernitious euill.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. De Ciu. Dei.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ipſum extolli, iam deijci eſt, Pride's very riſe, is her very downefall.</hi> But aboue all things, let vs not bee proud in <hi>Prayer,</hi> with the <hi>Phariſee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 18. 11.</note> VVhen the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſhines through the <hi>Caſement</hi> on the <hi>Wall, Shall</hi> the <hi>Wall</hi> ſtand vp, and ſay, <hi>It is I that ſend forth theſe beames,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 28. 36.</note> Holineſſe to the Lord,</hi> but <hi>Man</hi> can chalenge nothing as his <hi>Owne,</hi> but <hi>Sinne,</hi> and <hi>Frailty.</hi> But let vs paſſe on to the laſt <hi>Repulſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Hee anſwered, and ſaid, It is not good to take the Childrens bread, and to caſt it to Dogges.</hi> Here our Sauiour anſweres to her <hi>Lord help me,</hi> but more roughly, and ſeuerely, then euer <hi>Hee</hi> did before; for now <hi>Hee</hi> beginnes to chide, and ſneap her, as if ſhee were an vnmannerly <hi>Puppie.</hi> The purport of his ſpeech is this. <hi>Woman,</hi> I pray thee hold thy tongue, and ſhew not thy ſelfe ſo violent, and vnreaſonable. What grace ſoeuer is giuen me of my <hi>Father</hi> to bee diſpenſed, is to be exhibted diſtinctly to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> leſt they bee defrauded of their proper right: for <hi>my Father is the Father of Abrahams poſterity onely.</hi> Truth it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21044:19"/> is that the very <hi>Infidels</hi> find him by his <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> to be a <hi>Father;</hi> but <hi>Adoption,</hi> and other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall benediction is to be conferred peculiarly on the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Now verily it were an vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deed, to take the priuiledges of children, and to caſt them to ſuch as thee, who being without GOD in the world, art to bee kenne'ld vp mongſt <hi>Dogges.</hi> Howbeit, if thou hadſt not dealt ſo prepoſterouſly, much might haue been; if thou hadſt ſtaid till the <hi>Children</hi> had dined, happily thou mightſt haue light vpon ſome frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but to ſnatch of the diſhes in the midſt of dinner, betokens a ſhameleſſe malapertneſſe, and a preſumptuous rudeneſſe.</p>
            <p>See heere <hi>(Beloued)</hi> what we <hi>Gentiles</hi> were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we knew <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Let it not offend your eares, wee were no better then <hi>Curre-dogges,</hi> and ſo are all at this day, that liue, and die, without <hi>Him.</hi> Husbandmen, Yeomen, Gentlemen, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, Learned men, Valiant men, all <hi>Dogges</hi> without <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Now what more ignominious, and opprobrious then the name of <hi>Dogge? Am I a Doggeſ-head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.</note> ſaith <hi>Abner</hi> to <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> that thou accounteſt of me ſo baſely?</p>
            <p>Within the circuit of this our Church are found certaine <hi>Dogges</hi> that trouble, and annoy her. The firſt are thoſe Pricke-ear'd <hi>Curres</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Barke at the <hi>Moone,</hi> Nay at <hi>Him</hi> that made the <hi>Moone;</hi> to whom if you offer the <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7. 6. Prou. 30. 31.</note> they will turne againe, and all to rent you. Yet as if they were thoſe well-going <hi>Grey-hounds</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21044:19"/> that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes of, they haue veluet collars, richly ſtudded. They would bee look't to: for they are the true Scholers of thoſe falſe Apoſtles whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>Dogges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 2.</note> in the <hi>third</hi> to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> and the <hi>ſecond verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Dogge (who is like to leape ſhort of the Kingdome of <hi>Heauen)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22. 15.</note> is the outragious <hi>Swearer,</hi> who vpon euery ſmall occaſion, leapes at the throat of GODS moſt ſacred Maieſty, and giues him a ſhake by the boſome. O Iudges! ô Magiſtrates! why doe yee tyth <hi>Mint,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe,</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23. 23.</note> and leaue the weightier mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the law; condemne the <hi>Starueling</hi> for ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſheepe, and let the <hi>Blaſphemer</hi> go vntouch't, who ſets vp the cocke, and diſcharges his Piſtoll in the face of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Theſe things ought yee to haue done, and not haue left the other vndone. Ah, noble Prince HENRY (whoſe very name ſtill makes my heart to bleede afreſh) wee may thanke our <hi>Court-oathes,</hi> as one chiefe cauſe of thine vntimely death. But that God, that in wrath thinketh vpon mercy, hath from thy aſhes raiſ'd vp another <hi>Phoenix.<note place="margin">Deut. 33. 16.</note> The good will of Him that dwelt in the Buſh, come vpon his head, euen vpon the top of his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another <hi>Dogge</hi> is he that cauſeleſly railes on men in <hi>Authoritie;</hi> and this is no yelping Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, no little Whippit, but a deepe-mouth'd hound, or baying Maſtiue. Thus <hi>Shimei</hi> bids <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Come out, come out,</hi> as if he were a <hi>Dogge,</hi> when <hi>Shimei</hi> indeed was the the <hi>Dogge,</hi> as the ſonne of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21044:20"/> 
               <hi>Zeruiah</hi> calls him.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Dogge</hi> is the licentious liuer, who vpon ſome touch, goes ſoftly for a while;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none, returnes vnto his vomit. Thus the ſtinking <hi>Drunkard</hi> (for ſo the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> termes him)<note place="margin">Hoſea. 4. 18.</note> inflamed with Wine, neighes, and whinnies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his neighbours wife, (to vſe the phraſe of the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi>)<note place="margin">Ier. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and bleſſes himſelfe very deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately in his ſinne. Tuſh (ſaith he) GOD doth not ſee me, or cannot puniſh me, or will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me: by the firſt, making him a blind GOD: by the the ſecond, a lame GOD: by the third, an vnrighteous GOD. At laſt, God viſits him with a ſharpe diſeaſe, that wakens vp his conſcience, and then, <hi>ſicke, ſicke:</hi> and then, if GOD will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him, vntill a longer day, oh what a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> courſe he vowes to take! GOD proues him; he mends: In body? yes: in manners? no; no more the <hi>Pharaoh</hi> after then plagues remoouall.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Dogge</hi> we finde in the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> and this is the <hi>Dumb Dogge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 56. 10.</note> A <hi>Dogge</hi> and <hi>Dumb? Hem Dromo? Dromo!</hi> come hither! to the beame with him. What? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a keeper of the houſe,</hi> and not giue warning of the <hi>Theefe?</hi> This <hi>Dogge</hi> is the vnconſcionable <hi>Miniſter,</hi> that opens not his mouth for the ſafegard of his people; who knowes not the very firſt words of the <hi>Accidence;</hi> for were he but acquainted with IN SPEECH, it were iniuſtice to charge him with dumbneſſe. A very vnprofitable member. For there are <hi>Three</hi> things, which if they want <hi>tongues,</hi> are good for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21044:20"/> nothing; a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> a <hi>Dogge,</hi> and a <hi>Iewes-Trumpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remaineth now, that we conſider how this <hi>Woman</hi> digeſts this vngentle anſwere of <hi>Chriſt. And ſhe ſaid, Truth Lord; yet the Dogges eate of the crumbes that fall from their Maſters Table.</hi> In moe words, thus: Lord, I am a <hi>Dogge,</hi> I willingly confeſſe it; nay more, I confirme it; and with all my heart I acknowledge the <hi>Iewes</hi> to be thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, fed at thine owne Table, with variety of Heauenly Diſhes. Neither do I enuy them. Let me (poore ſoule) but gather vp the ſcrappes that fall from their Table at all aduenture, I craue no more.</p>
            <p>No man in the world could deuiſe a fitter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwer; for the grace of God was neuer dam'd vp ſo ſtrictly from the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but that ſome droppes ouer-flowed to them, as may be ſeene in <hi>Rahab, Ruth, Naaman,</hi> the <hi>Niniuites.</hi> And here againe the vnfatigableneſſe of her <hi>Faith</hi> preſents it ſelfe to our view. She followes and cries, and cries and followes, but what? The <hi>Solicited</hi> is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, the <hi>Diſciples</hi> grumble, ſhe is not of the <hi>Fold,</hi> ſhe is a <hi>Dogge.</hi> Who is a <hi>Dogge?</hi> A deuout and ſanctified <hi>Woman.</hi> And who calls her <hi>Dogge? Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>Sanctuary of Soules.</hi> It's nothing to ſwim in a warme bath; but to endure the Surges, and tumbling billows of the Sea, that's the man. To beleeue that GOD is thy GOD, and loues thee as the <hi>Apple</hi> of his eye, when he calls thee <hi>Dogge,</hi> and grindes thee to powder, that's the <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21044:21"/>
            <p>To end this <hi>ſecond</hi> part: this <hi>Woman</hi> ſuckes hony out of gall, and like a good <hi>Logician</hi> preſſes him with this <hi>Syllogiſme:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Dog is to haue the crums of his Maſters Table: I am the Iewes Dogge,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore. I am to haue the crummes of their table.</hi> The <hi>Maior</hi> is taken from the law of <hi>Nature,</hi> the <hi>Minor</hi> from thine owne words: what ſayſt thou, Lord? anſwere me: doſt thou <hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>diſtinguiſh?</hi> Neither. He did not anſwer the Argument; nay, (with reuerence be it ſpoken) he could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere it: for then he ſhould haue denied mercy to the <hi>Penitent,</hi> and ſo contradicted himſelfe, which had been an <hi>Impotencie.</hi> This of the EPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TASIS.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> is contained in the laſt words of the Text, Then <hi>Ieſus</hi> anſwered and ſaid vnto her, <hi>O woman! great is thy faith; bee it vnto thee euen as thou wilt.</hi> Where our <hi>Sauiour</hi> firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends this <hi>Woman,</hi> and that with an admiration; <hi>O woman!</hi> neuer in my life met I with ſuch an <hi>Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> thou paſſeſt of all that euer I knew; veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I haue not found ſuch <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Thou art able by thy knocking, and importunitie to make one riſe out of his bed, from his children at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, to lend thee <hi>three</hi> loaues.<note place="margin">Luke 11. 5. Luke 18. 5.</note> Thou doeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to compell an vnrighteous <hi>Iudge</hi> to doe thee iuſtice; much more a righteous one to ſhew thee fauour.</p>
            <p>O the bountifulneſſe of GOD! when we haue done all we can,<note place="margin">Luke 17. 10.</note> we are but vnprofitable ſeruants;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21044:21"/> yet he paſſeth by all our infirmities, and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all our good; rewardeth? yea, and applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. Thus the thriftie <hi>Seruant,</hi> that had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proou'd his <hi>Maſters Talents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25. 23.</note> hath an <hi>Euge</hi> for his paines: It is well done, good ſeruant, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. What a ſingular incouragement is here to well-doing? Ay <hi>Caitiues!</hi> ah <hi>Slacke-graces!</hi> how ſlothfull are we in our <hi>Maſters</hi> buſineſſe! ah <hi>Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagates,</hi> like <hi>Oneſimus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philem.</hi>
               </note> nay would to GOD wee were like <hi>Oneſimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for what extols hee this <hi>Woman</hi> thus? For her <hi>Faith.</hi> What <hi>Faith?</hi> That which <hi>Iuſtified</hi> her before GOD. But here's onely a ſute for a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefit, what though? That nothing lets, but that by the ſame <hi>Faith</hi> that laid hold on ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, ſhee beleeued alſo the recouery of her daughter;<note place="margin">Rom. 4. 19.</note> euen as <hi>Abraham</hi> by a <hi>Iuſtifying faith,</hi> was perſwaded of a <hi>Sonne</hi> in his old age. The whole tenor of the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> imports thus much, whether you conſider the <hi>Obiect</hi> of her <hi>Faith,</hi> or the <hi>Temper</hi> of it, or the <hi>Strength,</hi> or <hi>Effects;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which the laſt is moſt plaine for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: for it ſhewes that by <hi>this Faith,</hi> ſhe might obtaine whatſoeuer ſhee would; now who doubts, but ſhe would haue the forgiueneſſe of her ſinnes, without the which ſhee were more then moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>The next way then to be honoured of GOD, is to honour GOD;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.</note> and the next way to honour GOD, is <hi>Faith,</hi> which aſſures me that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath loued <hi>ME,</hi> and giuen <hi>Himſelfe</hi> for <hi>ME;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20.</note> and with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21044:22"/> 
               <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> all things: and all this <hi>He</hi> doth alone,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 32. Heb. 1. 3. Iſaiah 63. 3.</note> treading the Wine-preſſe <hi>ALONE,</hi> without helpe of <hi>Angels,</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> of <hi>Works:</hi> for <hi>Angels</hi> are but ſeruants, <hi>Men</hi> euer typing, and <hi>Workes</hi> not workers, but markes of our ſaluation. This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (as <hi>Staupitius</hi> well noteth) muſt needs be ſound, and the <hi>Religion</hi> that maintaines it, <hi>Pure,</hi> and <hi>vndefiled:</hi> for it exalts GODS glory aboue the Heauens, and humbles man to the duſt of death. Therefore is <hi>Abel</hi> commended for his <hi>Faith, Enoch</hi> for his <hi>Faith, Noah</hi> for his <hi>Faith, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> for their <hi>Faith, Moſes</hi> (the <hi>Law giuer)</hi> for his <hi>Faith; Rahab, Gedeon, Barac, Sampſon, Iephta, Dauid, Samuel</hi> for their <hi>Faith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> all for their <hi>Faith,</hi> and all in one Chapter.</p>
            <p>If here it be ſpitefully obiected, that we prate ſo much of <hi>Faith,</hi> that we haue pack't <hi>Good-Workes</hi> out of the Countrey; be it anſwered, that this is nothing but <hi>Wood ſere,</hi> or <hi>Cuckow-ſpit,</hi> the froth of rage, with a worme in the midſt of it. For wee doubt not to affirme, with <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>The fruit, and profit of one onely worke, which a Chriſtian doth in faith, and through faith, is to bee eſteemed more pretious then Heauen and Earth.</hi> Onely we exclude <hi>Good workes</hi> from our <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the law, becauſe therein nothing doth, nor can concurre with the <hi>Merit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And this is the very Argument of that excellent <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> to the <hi>Galatians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 11. 2. 11.</note> (which S. <hi>Paul</hi> writ with his owne hand) and for which he withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> to his face.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luth.</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </note> For as <hi>Luther</hi> (in an holy zeale, caſting
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21044:22"/> out flames of fire) ſaith; What is <hi>Peter?</hi> What is <hi>Paul?</hi> What is an <hi>Angell</hi> from heauen? What are all other creatures to the <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> A point ſo perſpicuous, and praevalent, that euen <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe (the <hi>Milo</hi> that beares the <hi>Pope</hi> vpon his ſhoulder) is forc'd to yeeld to it. His words are theſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>if. lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>In regard of the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Mans owne righteouſneſſe, and for feare of vaine-glory, it is the ſafeſt way to repoſe our whole confidence in the ONELY mercy, and goodneſſe of</hi> GOD.</p>
            <p>Now where we are charg'd, that the beating vpon the poynt of <hi>Faith,</hi> hath baniſhed <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes;</hi> we auouch it to be the ſpeciall way both to breed and cheriſh them. In this preſent <hi>Text</hi> is a <hi>Cluſter</hi> of <hi>Good-workes,</hi> farre more pleaſant to behold,<note place="margin">Numb. 13. 24.</note> then that of <hi>Grapes,</hi> which the two <hi>Spies</hi> brought on their ſhoulders, on a barre from the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Here is finding of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> crying cleare-out after <hi>Chriſt:</hi> here is <hi>Loue,</hi> here is <hi>Zeale,</hi> here is <hi>Patience,</hi> here is <hi>Prayer,</hi> here is <hi>Humilitie,</hi> here is <hi>Modeſty,</hi> here is <hi>Sincerity,</hi> here is <hi>Perſeuerance,</hi> and other ſparkes of <hi>Grace,</hi> that lie hidden, vnder the aſhes, which if you ſtirre, will flye aloft, &amp; crackle about your eares. What is the cauſe of all theſe <hi>Good deeds? Faith.</hi> For, can the <hi>Fruit</hi> be good, till the <hi>Tree</hi> be good? Can the <hi>Tree</hi> bee good, till the <hi>Sap</hi> bee good? Is not <hi>Man</hi> a <hi>Tree</hi> with the root vpward? Is it not <hi>Reaſon</hi> that makes a <hi>Man, Faith</hi> that makes a <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> Is not this <hi>Paules</hi> method in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21044:23"/> all his <hi>Epiſtles?</hi> Spends he not <hi>Eleuen</hi> Chapters in that to the <hi>Romans,</hi> in laying the foundation of <hi>Faith,</hi> before he build on it with exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>good life,</hi> which he performs but in fiue chapters? Ile tel thee, proud man, thou that ſwelleſt now in the confidence of thy works; when <hi>ſorrow</hi> comes, and the <hi>Law</hi> ſtrikes vp a fearefull <hi>Alarum</hi> againſt thee, thou ſhalt be ready to peake aſide, &amp; to ſpy out ſome bauke in an <hi>Out-houſe,</hi> whereon to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 1.</note> For, being <hi>iuſtified by Faith,</hi> wee haue <hi>peace with God;</hi> the <hi>Accent</hi> is vpon <hi>Faith,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> without which, without <hi>whom alone,</hi> we ſhall neuer haue <hi>peace of conſcience:</hi> but when it is <hi>Morning,</hi> we ſhal wiſh it were <hi>Euening;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 67.</note> and when it is <hi>Euening,</hi> we ſhal wiſh it were <hi>Morning;</hi> when we are in the <hi>Countrey,</hi> we ſhall long to be in the <hi>Citie;</hi> and when we are in the <hi>Citie,</hi> we ſhall long to be in the <hi>Countrey:</hi> changing the <hi>Place,</hi> but not changing the <hi>Paine;</hi> becauſe the forked arrow of GODS <hi>Vengeance</hi> ſtickes faſt in our ſide.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Orient Pearle,</hi> this <hi>Womans Faith,</hi> is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther magnified by the <hi>Greatneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Dictator</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſaid well,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Eth.</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Faireneſſe conſiſts in Greatneſſe.</hi> For a little houſe (though curious in the Frame) may bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Pretty,</hi> neuer <hi>Sumptuous.</hi> Now this <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> implies <hi>Degrees:</hi> For ſome are ſtrong, and Inuincible, as this <hi>Woman,</hi> who <hi>aboue Hope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued vnder Hope:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 18.</note> Others weake, as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> before <hi>CHRISTS Reſurrection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 9. 23.</note> So then wee muſt imitate the good man in Saint <hi>Marke,</hi> who
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21044:23"/> cryed with teares, <hi>Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This of the <hi>Commendation</hi> of the <hi>Womans Faith:</hi> now followes the <hi>Cheerefull Grant</hi> of <hi>Her Deſire; Be it vnto thee, euen as thou wilt.</hi> Do but aske and haue; The Deuill is gone out of thy Daughter; want'ſt thou any thing elſe? <hi>Competency? Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Heauen?</hi> Take it, take <hi>Mee</hi> and all, and all becauſe thou haſt wraſtled with <hi>Mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 28.</note> like <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ouercome <hi>Mee. Beloued Brethren!</hi> You that by vertue of this <hi>Faith,</hi> may aske what you will, and obtaine what you aske, let me this once be <hi>Yee All Repreſentatiuely,</hi> and in your ſtead beg for You and Mee, ſome precious thing that's worth the crauing.</p>
            <p>It ſhall not be <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> for that laſts but an inch of time, and what are we the better to play, and skip, like fiſh in the Riuer <hi>Iordan,</hi> and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to fall into the <hi>Dead Sea?</hi> It ſhall not be <hi>Honor,</hi> for that is a thing without vs, not in our owne poſſeſſion. It ſhall not bee mony, for (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith) it makes one ſigh at a Feaſt, and at Night when he ſinkes into his downe-bed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vigilat in Pluma,</hi> he lies broad waken. Theſe <hi>Three</hi> wiſh I not for You, and Mee, for they cannot laſt, nor ſecure the conſcience, nor ſatisfie the vnlimited deſire of the ſoule: But <hi>One Thing</hi> haue I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which I will ſtill require, and that is, <hi>The fruition of the Comforts that are in CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Happineſſe</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> aſpir'd to, in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21044:24"/> the third to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> the 7 and 8 verſes:<note place="margin">Philip. 3. 7. 8.</note> (a <hi>Text</hi> worthy to bee written in <hi>Golden,</hi> nay, in <hi>Heauenly Letters.) I haue counted</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>All Things loſſe fpr Chriſt. Quae</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which <hi>All things?</hi> That I was not an <hi>Infidell:</hi> but <hi>Circumciſed;</hi> and that not when I was a Stripling, a Man, an old Man, as were the <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> but the <hi>Eighth Day,</hi> according to the preſcript of the <hi>Law;</hi> That I was not of an ordinary <hi>Tribe,</hi> but of <hi>BENIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIN,</hi> whence ſprang the firſt <hi>King,</hi> and which claue to <hi>IVDAH,</hi> when the <hi>Ten Tribes</hi> fell away: That I was not lately deſcended from the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> but very anciently from the Loynes of <hi>Iacob:</hi> That I was not of a meane Place, but a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> the moſt famous of Sects, for the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Sanctimony</hi> and <hi>Learning;</hi> That I was not <hi>Cold,</hi> or <hi>Luke-warme,</hi> in my <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> but <hi>Wallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> and <hi>Running</hi> ouer with heate of <hi>Zeale,</hi> euen to the perſecution of the <hi>Church:</hi> That I was not of a <hi>ſpotted</hi> or <hi>indifferent</hi> Carriage, but of a <hi>cleare</hi> and <hi>vnſuſpected</hi> life: All theſe, theſe All, and All things elſe (except my <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> in CHRIST) as the <hi>Priuiledge</hi> of mine <hi>Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> my inward Vertues, and workes of <hi>Grace, Haue I counted loſt for</hi> CHRIST. Yea <hi>Paul,</hi> you <hi>Haue,</hi> but <hi>DOE</hi> you <hi>Now?</hi> Is not your mind al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered? Yea doubtleſſe (I know what I ſay) <hi>I DOE count All things loſſe,</hi> and more then that, I <hi>Haue ſuffered the loſſe of All things,</hi> and haue throwne them <hi>Ouer board,</hi> as Wares into the <hi>Sea,</hi> to ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten my ſelfe of <hi>Them.</hi> Yea, but do you not now
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21044:24"/> repent, as <hi>Marriners</hi> are wont in the like caſe, when they come to Shore? <hi>Not I,</hi> not a whit; Farewell they; I am glad I am rid of Them: For what are they, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but <hi>Droſſe,</hi> but <hi>Rubbiſh,</hi> but <hi>Offall,</hi> but <hi>Refuſe,</hi> but <hi>Garbage,</hi> but <hi>DYNG,</hi> in reſpect of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Then more, and more, do I find and perceiue, that <hi>All</hi> things to CHRIST are but vaine, and irkſome: and that without <hi>Him,</hi> the moſt Iuſhious pleaſures, and clyming preferments, are but weeping Ioyes, and noble Miſeries. <hi>O how Honourable is Hee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 9. 6.</note> For his Name is <hi>Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Counceller, the Mightie</hi> GOD, <hi>the Euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father, the Prince of Peace.</hi> O how Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious is <hi>Hee,</hi> and with what a grace doth <hi>Hee</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph!<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 63. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Who is this that comes from Edom, with Red Garments from Bozrah?</hi> O how <hi>Rich</hi> is Hee,<note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1. 2. Cor. 3.</note> for Hee is <hi>Shaddai,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>All-Sufficient,</hi> though being <hi>Rich</hi> Hee became <hi>Poore</hi> for vs. O how comfortable is Hee,<note place="margin">Reu. 22. 16. Pſal. 45. 8.</note> for Hee is not a <hi>Blaſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaree,</hi> nor a <hi>Night-Starre,</hi> but the <hi>Morning Starre,</hi> and that not clouded, but bright, and reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.<note place="margin">Cant. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>O how ſweet is Hee, and how all his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſmell of Mirrh, Aloes, and Caſsia;</hi> His name is as an <hi>Oyntment</hi> powred out, therefore the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines</hi> loue Him.<note place="margin">Cant. 5. 10.</note> O how <hi>Amiable</hi> is He, for He is <hi>White, and Ruddie, the chiefeſt of ten thouſand; His Head is as fine Gold, his Lockes are curled, and blacke as a Rauen.</hi> O how louing is <hi>He,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 6.</note> for his <hi>left hand</hi> is vnder his <hi>Spouſes</hi> head, and his <hi>Right hand</hi> doth embrace her. O, he hath lou'd vs, (as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21044:25"/> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> noteth)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sweetly, Wiſely, Strongly: Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> for Hee tooke vpon Him our Nature: <hi>Wiſely,</hi> for Hee tooke not on Him the corruption of our Nature: <hi>Strongly,</hi> for Hee gaue vp His Life for our ſakes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 8. 1. 6. 2. 5.</note>O CHRIST, <hi>That thou wert as my Brother, that ſuckt the breaſts of my Mother, that I might finde thee, and kiſſe thee. Set me as a Seale on thine heart, and as a Sgnet vpon thine Arme. Stay mee with Flaggons, and comfort me with Apples, for I am ſicke of loue.</hi> Let me borrow the words of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Igna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Come Fire, come Gibber, come tearing with wilde Beaſts, come craſhing of my Bones in peeces, come drawing my foure Quarters aſunder, come grinding my whole Body to powder; nay, come the torments of the Deuill, ſo I may but <hi>Winne</hi> CHRIST, <hi>Lord,</hi> let mee ſee Thee, that I may die; or rather, let mee die, that I may ſee Thee; yet with humble ſubmiſſion to thy holy Will, leſt otherwiſe I die, and doe not ſee thee. To this our deere, and bleſſed <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> together with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> bee all Honour, and Glory, Now and Euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21044:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
